Guide to the Byron Rufus Newton Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Byron Rufus Newton papers
1882-1938
MS 374
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
5
(7 boxes, 1 folio)
Corrrespondence, writings, notes, printed materials, clippings, photographs, financial papers, and memorabilia of Byron R. Newton, journalist and official in the Democratic Party. The papers relate largely to Democratic Party politics from 1910-1933, though there is also material relating to the early history of aviation in this country. Correspondents of note include Newton D. Baker, Charles W. Fairbanks, William G. McAdoo, William F. McCombs, Franklin D. Roosevelt, Theodore Roosevelt, Woodrow Wilson, and Wilbur and Orville Wright.
Newton, Byron Rufus, 1861-1938
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Margaret L. Newton, 1969.
Arrangement
Arranged in three series: I. Correspondence. II. Writings, Memoirs, and Notes. III. Special Files.
Scope and Contents
The Byron R. Newton Papers consist of seven archive boxes containing correspondence, manuscript articles, notes, and poems; a quantity of printed articles and newspaper clippings (mostly articles written by Newton); and a small quantity of photographs, financial materials, and memorabilia. Although small, the collection provides a rich source of information for the scholar interested in Democratic party politics from about 1910 to 1933. In addition, there are interesting materials concerning early aviation, William G. McAdoo's fight to build a railroad tunnel beneath the Hudson River, and the early use of political polls and opinion surveys, as well as the practice and techniques of public relations by Newton, one of its earliest practicioners.
The collection is divided into three series: Correspondence; Writings, Memoirs, and Notes; and Special Files. The first series, Correspondence, contains revealing materials on the Wilson election campaign of 1912, and on the fights for the nominations and the subsequent election campaigns in the years 1924, 1928, and 1932. Newton's correspondence with Newton D. Baker (16 items) is especially valuable for the insights it provides into the campaign strategies and behind-the-scenes maneuvering of various candidates, especially Franklin D. Roosevelt, William McAdoo, and Woodrow Wilson for the presidential nomination of the Democratic party. In addition, a number of important issues are discussed, notably those pertaining to the regulation of the railroads and utilities, oil interests, municipal reform, the influence of Tammany Hall in the Democratic party, and corruption in city governments. The predominant issue, however, is that of prohibition, a question of vital interest to McAdoo. Much of the correspondence between Newton and McAdoo, in particular, deals with the effect of prohibition on the election campaigns of 1928 and 1932, as well as its effect on the question of "law and order." The influence of Tammany Hall and its alleged control of Al Smith and then governor Franklin D. Roosevelt are also topics prominent in Newton's correspondence during the late 1920s and early 1930s.
In addition to McAdoo, Roosevelt, and Baker, other prominent correspondents represented in the collection are: Charles W. Fairbanks (6 items); the Aero Club of America (14 items); William F. McCombs (10 items); Theodore Roosevelt (5 items); Allan A. Ryan (4 items); Woodrow Wilson (ca. 23 items); and Wilbur, Orville, and Katherine Wright (4 items). A small group of "Correspondence of Others" consists primarily of materials relating to the Wilson presidential campaign of 1912 and includes the correspondence of Woodrow Wilson (7 items), William McAdoo (8 items), and William F. McCombs (4 items).
The second series, Writings, Memoirs, and Notes, consists mainly of articles written by Newton as newspaper reporter, although there are also some magazine articles, memoirs of his experiences during the Spanish-American War, and various speeches, poems, and some notes on the death of McKinley, an event covered by Newton while he was a reporter.
Special Files consists primarily of expense accounts, financial records of Newton (and to a lesser extent of the Wilson campaign of 1912), and personal and family papers and memorabilia. In addition, there are photographs of McAdoo and the families of Newton and Woodrow Wilson. Most important in this series, however, are three folders of materials pertaining to the Wilson campaign of 1912 and a small amount on the campaign of 1916.
* The Newton Papers contain nothing from the period from 1933 until Newton's death in 1938.
Biographical / Historical
Byron R. Newton (1861-1938) was born in Alleghany County, New York, and attended Oberlin College. After his graduation, he returned to upper New York State and pursued journalism. In 1886, he was employed by the Buffalo News, for which he worked until the Spanish-American War. In the summer of 1898, he went to Cuba as an Associated Press correspondent.
Shortly after his return he was appointed to represent American newspapers at the British-American Joint High Commission session in Quebec. He continued working for the Buffalo News until he became Secretary of the Pan American Exposition in 1901.
In 1902, he accepted a position with the New York Herald. Newton was among the first to recognize the importance of the early experiments in aviation, and his interest gained much favorable publicity for this new field. Also while working for the Herald, Newton became acquainted with William Gibbs McAdoo, who was then attempting to implement his widely-ridiculed plan to build railroad tunnels under the Hudson River. Newton took McAdoo's plan seriously and reported it favorably, reversing public opinion. The two men became fast friends.
In 1910, Newton resigned his newspaper position to work for the election of Woodrow Wilson. Both Newton and McAdoo served in high posts at Democratic headquarters. After Wilson's inauguration, Newton served briefly as private secretary to McAdoo before he was appointed Assistant Secretary of the Treasury. He was appointed Collector of Customs of the Port of New York in 1917 and remained there while Wilson was in office.
During the 1920s Newton was retained first by the New York State Chamber of Commerce, then by the Anthracite Coal Operators in public relations capacities. Later in the decade he took an interest in the petroleum industry, but the nature of his involvement with it is unclear.
Byron R. Newton died in 1938.
Aeronautics -- History; Prohibition; New York (State) -- Politics and government; United States -- Politics and government -- 1919-1933; Journalists; Politicians; Baker, Newton Diehl, 1871-1937; Baker, Ray Stannard, 1870-1946; Bennett, James Gordon, 1795-1872; Fairbanks, Charles W. (Charles Warren), 1852-1918; Howe, Louis M. (Louis McHenry), 1871-1936; McAdoo, W. G. (William Gibbs), 1863-1941; McCombs, William Frank, 1875-1921; Newton, Byron Rufus, 1861-1938; Roosevelt, Franklin D. (Franklin Delano), 1882-1945; Roosevelt, Theodore, 1858-1919; Tumulty, Joseph P. (Joseph Patrick), 1879-1954; Wilson, Woodrow, 1856-1924; Wright, Orville, 1871-1948; Wright, Wilbur, 1867-1912; Democratic Party (U.S.)
- Correspondence, 1882-1883, 1885-1933, 1938; Series I; 1.5 linear feet (3 boxes)
  Scope and Contents
  CORRESPONDENCE is divided into two sections. The first, "General Correspondence," is arranged alphabetically by name of the person with whom Newton was corresponding. The second, "Correspondence of Others," is arranged alphabetically by name of the more prominent of the two correspondents, although the name of the other correspondent also appears in the register and on the folder.
  - General Correspondence
    - Aero Club of America (14 items), 1913, 1914, 1917 (Box 1, Folder 1)
      General
      See also: box 3, folder 203
    - American Magazine (1 item), 1907 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Andrews, H. V.
      See: box 1, folder 39
    - Andrews, Kenneth
      See: box 1, folder 51
    - Anktell, Thomas Jackson (4 items), 1912 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Anthracite Coal Mine Operators
      See: box 2, folder 104,
    - Associated Press (4 items), 1898, 1911-1912 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Astor, Helen (1 item), 1920 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Auman, William (1 item), 1900 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Bacheller, Irving (1 item), 1903 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Bagg, G. R.
      See: box 3, folder 173
    - Bailey, L. H. (1 item), 1908 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Baker, Newton D. (16 items), 1930-1933 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Baker, Ray Stannard (2 items), 1903, 1929 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Baltimore Sun (1 item), 1914 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Baner, Katharine S. (1 item), 1909 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Barrymore, John (1 item), 1914 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Bayside Yacht Club (1 item), 1913 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Bennett, James Gordon
      See: box 2, folder 125
    - Berthulf, Capt. E. P., U.S.C.G. (1 item), 1913 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Binder, J. W. (ca. 2 items) (Box 1, Folder 21)
      See also: box 3, folder 199 See also: box 3, folder 208
    - Bolton, Joe (1 item), 1914 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - Bresbaur(?), A.
      See: box 2, folder 126
    - Bridgeman(?), J. W.
      See: box 1, folder 27
    - Brooks, James J.
    - Brown, Capt. James R., U.S.C.G. (1 item), undated (Box 1, Folder 26)
    - Buffalo Courier (3 items), 1888-1889 (Box 1, Folder 27)
    - Buffalo Express (ca. 4 items), 1887, 1888, 1898, 1899 (Box 1, Folder 28)
      See also: box 2, folder 118
    - Buffalo News, Evening News (ca. 7 items), 1886, 1887, 1890[?], 1898 (Box 1, Folder 29)
      See also: box 2, folder 118 See also: box 3, folder 198
    - Buffalo Times (3 items), 1898[?], 1911, 1912 (Box 1, Folder 30)
      See also: box 3, folder 198
    - Butler, E. H.
      See: box 1, folder 29
    - Camden, B. H. (1 item), 1926 (Box 1, Folder 32)
    - Chambers, Julius
      See: box 2, folder 128
    - Chautauqua Lake Sunday School Assembly (1 item), 1882 (Box 1, Folder 34)
    - Circle Magazine (1 item), 1909 (Box 1, Folder 35)
    - Coffin, Dr. Howard E.
      See: box 1, folder 1 See also: box 3, folder 203
    - Cole, A. N.
      See: box 3, folder 184
    - Commercial Advertiser (3 items), 1887 (Box 1, Folder 38)
    - Country Calendar (1 item), 1904 (Box 1, Folder 39)
    - Crosby, E. W.
      See: box 1, folder 30
    - Cummings, Homer S.
      See: box 1, folder 47
    - Daniels, Josephus (1 item), 1915 (Box 1, Folder 42)
    - Davenport, Ben (1 item), 1890 (Box 1, Folder 43)
    - Dayton, J. Wilson, Realtor (3 items), 1927 (Box 1, Folder 44)
    - Democratic Club, National (1 item), 1911 (Box 1, Folder 45)
    - Democratic State Central Committee of Washington
      See: box 1, folder 77
    - Democratic National Committee (6 items), 1912, 1916 (Box 1, Folder 47)
    - Denver Post (1 item), 1916 (Box 1, Folder 48)
    - Diehl, Charles S. (1 item), 1898 (Box 1, Folder 49)
    - Dooley, A. J. (ca. 1 item), 1912 (Box 1, Folder 50)
      See also: box 3, folder 199
    - Doubleday, Page & Company (4 items), 1912, 1927 (Box 1, Folder 51)
    - Drew, Edward W.
    - Dril[?], Robert G.
      See: box 1, folder 48
    - Drummond, A. L.
    - Elizabeth (N.J.) Evening Times (2 items), 1912 (Box 1, Folder 55)
    - Essary, J. Fred
      See: box 1, folder 15
    - Fairbanks, Charles W. (6 items), 1898, 1900, 1904, 1908, 1912 (Box 1, Folder 57)
    - Farley, James A. (1 item), 1938 (Box 1, Folder 58)
    - Farrelly, R. E.
    - Field, Mary French (1 item), 1897 (Box 1, Folder 60)
    - Fitzgerald, John J. (?), Rep. of N.Y. (1 item), 1914 (Box 1, Folder 61)
    - Fleming, Edwin
    - Franklin, Malcolm A. (?) (1 item), [1915?] (Box 1, Folder 63)
    - Gaynor, William J.
      See: box 2, folder 123
    - Glass, Carter, Sen. from Va. (1 item), 1922 (Box 1, Folder 65)
    - Gorman, William H. (1 item), 1927 (Box 1, Folder 66)
    - Graham, George Edward (1 item), 1906 (Box 1, Folder 67)
    - Green, Martin (1 item), undated (Box 1, Folder 68)
    - Greene, J. W.
      See: box 1, folder 28
    - Hague, Robert L. (4 items), 1927 (Box 1, Folder 70)
    - Hale, William B.
    - Hamilton, S. W. (1 item), 1927 (Box 1, Folder 72)
    - Hartman, Katharine (1 item), 1914 (Box 1, Folder 73)
    - Hawaii, Governor
      See: box 3, folder 140
    - Hawley, Alan R.
      See: box 1, folder 1
    - Head, Marguerite (2 items), 1927 (Box 1, Folder 76)
    - Heifner, Charles G. (ca. 3 items), 1912, undated (Box 1, Folder 77)
      See also: box 3, folder 209
    - Hillegras, H. C.
    - Hopkins, Samuel A. (1 item), 1901 (Box 1, Folder 79)
    - Hopper, B. N. (1 item), 1886 (Box 1, Folder 80)
    - Howe, Louis M. (7 items), 1932 (Box 1, Folder 81)
    - Howland, A. H.
      See: box 1, folder 35
    - Johnston, William
    - Judge Company (publishers), Editor (1 item), 1907 (Box 2, Folder 84)
    - Kendall, Frederick W.
      See: box 1, folder 28 See: box 2, folder 118
    - Kennedy, John J., Treasurer, State of New York (1 item), 1911 (Box 2, Folder 86)
    - Kinter, George H. (2 items), 1898 (Box 2, Folder 87)
    - LaGuardia, Marie and Fiorello H. (1 item), 1938 (Box 2, Folder 88)
    - LeGallienne, Richard (17 items), 1921, 1923, 1925-1926, undated (Box 2, Folder 89)
    - Lincoln, C. M.
    - Loeb, William, Jr. (2 items), 1904, 1909 (Box 2, Folder 91)
    - London Daily Express (1 item), 1900 (Box 2, Folder 92)
    - Ludlow, Helena E. (1 item), 1927 (Box 2, Folder 93)
    - Lyon, George F. (1 item), 1892 (Box 2, Folder 94)
    - McAdoo, William Gibbs (ca. 99 items)
      See also: box 3, folders 203-207
    - McClure's Magazine (ca. 2 items), 1899, 1900 (Box 2, Folder 98)
      See also: box 1, folder 14
    - McCombs, William F. (ca. 10 items), 1911-1912 (Box 2, Folder 99)
      See also: box 3, folders 208-210
    - McConkey, James G.
      See: box 1, folder 47 See also: box 3, folder 207
    - McQuiddy, J. C. (3 items), 1927 (Box 2, Folder 101)
    - Mack, Frank W.
      See: box 1, folder 7 See also: box 2, folder 118
    - Mack, Norman E.
    - Madeira, Percy C. (4 items), 1924, 1926, undated (Box 2, Folder 104)
    - Malone, Dudley Field (2 items), 1912, 1913 (Box 2, Folder 105)
    - Martin, Don (1 item), 1913 (Box 2, Folder 106)
    - Martin, James
      See: box 2, folder 127
    - Mason, Walt (1 item), February 26, n.y. (Box 2, Folder 108)
    - Measday, Walter (2 items), 1912 (Box 2, Folder 109)
    - Michigan Central Railroad Company (1 item), 1894 (Box 2, Folder 110)
    - Miller, Capt. Frederick C. (1 item), 1900 (Box 2, Folder 111)
    - Millholen, H. E.
      See: box 2, folder 124
    - Muldoon, William (1 item), 1910 (Box 2, Folder 113)
    - Nebraska State Senate
      See: box 3, folder 159
    - Negro National Anti-Taft League (1 item), 1912 (Box 2, Folder 115)
    - Nelson, J. B.
      See: box 1, folder 7
    - Nelson, Knute (1 item), 1914 (Box 2, Folder 117)
    - Newton, Byron Rufus (11 items), 1912 (Box 2, Folder 118)
    - Newton, John, 1912, 1913, 1914, undated (Box 2, Folder 119)
    - Newton, L C. (1 item), 1888 (Box 2, Folder 120)
    - Newton, Margaret (16 items), 1925, 1928-1931, undated (Box 2, Folder 121)
      See also: box 2, folder 122
    - Newton, Winifred Cattle (4 items), 1901, undated (Box 2, Folder 122)
    - New York City, Mayor of, 1911 (Box 2, Folder 123)
    - New York Evening Post (1 item), April 4, n.y. (Box 2, Folder 124)
    - New York Herald (8 items), 1902, 1906, 1908, 1909, 1914, undated (Box 2, Folder 125)
    - New York Journal (2 items), 1896, 1907 (Box 2, Folder 126)
    - New York Tribune (2 items), 1901 (Box 2, Folder 127)
    - New York World (8 items), 1885, 1890, 1912, undated (Box 2, Folder 128)
    - Nixon, S. F. (1 item), 1900 (Box 2, Folder 129)
    - Norton, James E.
      See: box 1, folder 38
    - Olawosky (?), S. E. (1 item), 1892 (Box 3, Folder 131)
    - Oliver, Frank (1 item), 1913 (Box 3, Folder 132)
    - Page, Arthur W.
    - Pasadena Star-News (3 items), 1927 (Box 3, Folder 134)
    - Pearson(?), C. A.
      See: box 2, folder 92
    - Phillips, J. S.
      See: box 1, folder 2
    - Pidgeon, Edward E. (1 item), 1906 (Box 3, Folder 137)
    - Pierce, Daniel T. (3 items), 1926, 1927 (Box 3, Folder 138)
    - Pierson, Charles R.
      See: box 2, folder 118
    - Pinkham, Lucius E. (2 items), 1915 (Box 3, Folder 140)
    - Post, Augustus
    - Prescott(?), J. O. (1 item), 1888 (Box 3, Folder 142)
    - Prisk, Charles H.
      See: box 3, folder 134
    - Roberts, Ellis H.
      See: box 3, folder 176
    - Roberts, Elmer
    - Rockwell(?), H. G. (1 item), 1911 (Box 3, Folder 146)
    - Roedell, Gustav A. (1 item), undated (Box 3, Folder 147)
    - Roosevelt, Franklin Delano (20 items), 1922, 1924, 1927-1930 (Box 3, Folder 148)
      See also: box 1, folder 81
    - Roosevelt, Theodore (5 items), 1898, 1900, 1910, 1912 (Box 3, Folder 149)
    - Roper, Daniel C. (1 item), 1938 (Box 3, Folder 150)
    - Russell, L. T.
      See: box 1, folder 55
    - Ryan, Allan A. (4 items), 1911-1913 (Box 3, Folder 152)
    - Scanlon, Jack (1 item), 1927 (Box 3, Folder 153)
    - Scott, Rufus
    - Scovel, Sylvester (1 item), 1898 (Box 3, Folder 155)
    - Secret Service Division, U. S. Treasury Dept
    - Selph, Colin M. (ca. 2 items), 1912 (Box 3, Folder 157)
      See also: box 3, folder 214
    - Severance, Frank H.
    - Smith, William H. (1 item), 1912 (Box 3, Folder 159)
    - Spencer, Israel (1 item), 1914 (Box 3, Folder 160)
    - Standard Oil of California
      See: box 2, folder 101
    - Standard Oil of New Jersey
      See: box 1, folder 70
    - State Charities Aid Association (1 item), 1909 (Box 3, Folder 163)
    - Stires, Ernest M. (1 item), 1938 (Box 3, Folder 164)
    - Stockbridge, F. S. (ca. 1 item), 1911 (Box 3, Folder 165)
      See also: box 3, folders 213-214
    - Storey, Elmer G. (3 items), 1927 (Box 3, Folder 166)
    - Stricker, Sidney G. (1 item), 1911 (Box 3, Folder 167)
    - Sutro, Adolph (1 item), 1892 (Box 3, Folder 168)
    - Swann, Thomas Wallace
      See: box 2, folder 115
    - Tabur, Harry P. (1 item), 1901 (Box 3, Folder 170)
    - Thomas, C. S. (1 item), 1912 (Box 3, Folder 171)
    - Thomson, T. Kennard (1 item), 1926 (Box 3, Folder 172)
    - Treasury Department, U. S., Secret Service Division (8 items), 1890-1891 (Box 3, Folder 173)
    - Tumulty, Joseph P. (ca. 7 items), 1912, 1913, 1916 (Box 3, Folder 174)
      See also: box 3, folder 193 See also: box 3, folder 215
    - Underwood, W. H.
      See: box 2, folder 110
    - Utica Morning Herald and Gazette (1 item), 1887 (Box 3, Folder 176)
    - Utter, Frank (1 item), 1912 (Box 3, Folder 177)
    - Vincent, J. H.
      See: box 1, folder 34
    - Walsh, Frank P. (1 item), 1912 (Box 3, Folder 179)
    - Wanette Enterprise (1 item), 1912 (Box 3, Folder 180)
    - Warren, C. W. (1 item), 1883 (Box 3, Folder 181)
    - Wells, H. S.
    - Wells, Rolla
    - Wellsville Daily Free Press (1 item), 1887 (Box 3, Folder 184)
    - West India Oil Company (1 item), 1927 (Box 3, Folder 185)
    - Wigham, Harry (1 item), 1912 (Box 3, Folder 186)
    - Whish, John D. (1 item), 1898 (Box 3, Folder 187)
    - White, J. D.
    - Willumsen(?), W.
      See: box 3, folder 185
    - Wilshire, Gaylord (2 items), 1907 (Box 3, Folder 190)
    - Wilson, Margaret W. (1 item), 1912 (Box 3, Folder 191)
    - Wilson, N. W. (1 item), 1891 (Box 3, Folder 192)
    - Wilson, Woodrow (ca. 23 items), 1911-1912, 1915-1916, 1918, 1920-1922 (Box 3, Folder 193)
      See also: box 3, folder 174 See also: box 3, folder 216
    - Wolcott, Dr. Charles D.
    - Wooten, June P. (2 items), 1911 (Box 3, Folder 195)
    - Wright, Wilbur, Orville, and Katharine (4 items), 1910, 1914, 1915 (Box 3, Folder 196)
    - Unidentified (4 items) (Box 3, Folder 197)
  - Correspondence of Others
    - Bennett, Mark from Henry "Pendragon" Sampson re: Griffiths, Charles W. (1 item), 1890 (Box 3, Folder 198)
    - Binder, J. W. to A. J. Dooley (1 item), 1911 (Box 3, Folder 199)
    - Butler, William T. to C. D. Kilborn, Editor, Nevada State Journal (1 item), 1912 (Box 3, Folder 200)
    - Butler, William T. to R. F. Milwoe (1 item), 1912 (Box 3, Folder 201)
    - Dickinson, Don M. to John J. Gifford, President, Woodrow Wilson Democratic League of N.J. (1 item), 1911 (Box 3, Folder 202)
    - McAdoo, William Gibbs
      - from/to Aero Club of America (3 items), 1917 (Box 3, Folder 203)
      - from William Jennings Bryan (1 item), 1913 (Box 3, Folder 204)
      - to George Creel (1 item), 1923 (Box 3, Folder 205)
      - to/from John J. Keegan (2 items), 1912 (Box 3, Folder 206)
        See also: box 3, folder 207
      - from James G. McConkey (1 item), 1912 (Box 3, Folder 207)
    - McCombs, William F.
      - to/from J. W. Binder (2 items), 1911 (Box 3, Folder 208)
      - from Charles G. Heifner (1 item), 1912 (Box 3, Folder 209)
      - from unidentified (1 item), undated (Box 3, Folder 210)
    - MacKenzie, W. to unidentified (1 item), 1898 (Box 3, Folder 211)
    - Millhollen, Charles to "Charley" (1 item), undated (Box 3, Folder 212)
    - Stockbridge, F. P.
      - from Charles W. Bryan (1 item), 1911 (Box 3, Folder 213)
      - from Colin M. Selph (1 item), 1911 (Box 3, Folder 214)
    - Tumulty, Joseph P. from Henry H. Klein (1 item), December 23, n.y. (Box 3, Folder 215)
    - Wilson, Woodrow from Alberta M. Hill, Bessie W. Thornby, and others (7 items), 1912 (Box 3, Folder 216)
- Writings, Memoirs and Notes, 1883-1888, (1889-1891), 1890-1898, 1900-1910, 1913-1917, 1925-1928; Series II; .75 linear feet (2 boxes)
  - American Landmark Series, No. 1-5 (syndicated column), 1885, undated (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Magazine articles, printed, 1902, 1908, 1909, undated (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Manuscript, typed: Anecdote about McAdoo, undated (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Manuscript, typed (2 copies): Concerning W. G. McAdoo's involvement in national politics, 1928 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Manuscript: "William Gibbs McAdoo,", undated (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Manuscript (2 copies): Concerning McAdoo and the Hudson River Tunnel System, undated (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Manuscript, typed: "Facts about the Hudson River Tunnel System,", undated (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Manuscripts for an article in Collier's concerning his position as Collector for the Port of New York, undated (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Manuscripts, miscellaneous, 1901, undated (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Memoirs: "Incidents of my Experience as a Correspondent of the Associated Press, during the Spanish-American War, the Summer of 1898,", 1900 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Newspaper articles, 1895 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Scrapbook of newspaper articles, 1889-1891 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Newspaper articles (Xerox copies of destroyed originals), 1884, 1885, 1886, 1890, 1892, 1893, 1898, 1900, 1901, 1902, 1913, undated (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Newspaper articles (2 items) which received special commendation: New York Herald, 1904 June 5, 1907 April [?] (Box 4, Folder 13a)
  - Newspaper articles, 1887, 1896, 1900, 1903, 1904, 1905[?], 1908, 1910, 1926, undated (Box 4, Folder 14)
    See also: box 8
  - Notes re: reading given by James Whitcomb Riley, Circa 1887 or 1888 (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - Notes re: President McKinley's death (Box 5, Folder 16)
  - Notes for statement re: Mrs. French, undated (Box 5, Folder 17)
  - Notes, miscellaneous, 1884, 1901, undated (Box 5, Folder 18)
  - Poems, 1883, 1893, 1895, circa 1898, 1913, 1915, 1917, 1926, undated (Box 5, Folder 19)
  - Speeches, radio talks, etc. re: Anthracite coal strike, Circa 1925-1926 (Box 5, Folder 20)
  - Speeches, miscellaneous, 1927, undated (Box 5, Folder 21)
  - Woodrow Wilson campaign materials
    See: box 7, folders 15-16
- Special Files, Circa 1880s, 1887, 1891-1927; Series III; .75 linear feet (2 boxes)
  General note
  Folio
  - Biographical: newspaper clippings about Byron Newton and Treasury Dept. activities
    - 1898, 1912-1918, 1920, 1927 (Box 6, Folder 1)